good evening everyone I'll now call to order this meeting of committees of City Council for March 3rd 2025 we'll begin with a roll call of members mr. Harris
yes madam president mr. men here mr. Roya here mr. Cleese yeah mr. Craig
misty is here mr. harsh here the president BK here councillor Craig is excused this evening a few reminders for everyone in attendance first please silence your phones and devices if you haven't done so already second this meeting and its participants are being recorded tonight we have meetings of committees of counsel there are no general public comment periods during this meeting however committee chairs will call for comments from the public on specific agenda items comments are limited to three minutes per speaker and must begin with your name and block of residence for our meeting record to keep time we'll be using a light here it'll turn green when a speaker begins turn yellow when there's one minute remaining and uh turn red when three minutes has been expended thank you in advance for allowing everyone equal time now we'll move to the approval of the minutes for the february 3rd 2025 meetings of committee so move second we have a motion and a second for our meeting minutes are are there any council comments on the minutes hearing none mr. Harris mr.
Metz hi mr. Arroyo hi mr. Cleese hi mr. yes hi mr. Hirsch hi
I'm president I all right our first committee this evening is personnel
councillor colleagues thank you madam president the personal committee has two items on the agenda for tonight the first item is the nomination of Stephen gross for appointment to the city revitalization and improvement zone authority mr groff is nominated due to his experience and a pair request of senator scott martin due to his impressive legal background leadership experience and dedication to the lancaster community so now i'll make i think i guess he's not here but oh could you please step for what please yes thank you thank you very much thank you very much yeah sure
well thank you very much for inviting me this evening I have not actually been to a City Council meeting or a committee's City Council meeting before so this is kind of my first first opportunity so I grew up in Lancaster County graduate of Warwick High School after law school I moved back after a short clerkship in Altoona moved back to Lancaster to start my legal career I've had a law practice here across actually from the the courthouse for over ten years I primarily do a lot of litigation including criminal defense and family law and some general business matters. I love Lancaster City. It's improved so much from when I was a kid. The only time I ever came really to Lancaster City with my parents, we would shop and go to lunch at Walton Chance. And sometimes my dad would go to what used to be TMB and he would drag me along. But it's incredible what's happened to Lancaster City and a lot of that's because we've had some great leadership over the years. Love working in Lancaster City, serving the people all over the county. I go outside of the county, too, but primarily my practice is focused in Lancaster. Personally, I live in Manhattan Township with my wife, Melissa, my son, Harrison, and my daughter, Olivia. They go to Manhattan Township. I was on the school board in Manhattan Township for about eight and a half years. Half of that was either as president or vice president, but I stepped down last year to just take some time. Eight and a half years was a long time. I'm currently on the board at UPMC. I've been on the board for about 15 years. Love that. I think this board is very interesting to me because it's completely different than what I've ever done before. It's very unique. I didn't know a lot about it, to be honest with you, so I had to obviously ask some people and do my own research, but it's really pretty incredible. I love working on boards. I think it's a great opportunity to collaborate with other people, to try to find solutions to problems that we may have and I'm sure looking forward to getting started I think I have to schedule an orientation the next few days so I'm looking forward to that but thanks again hopefully the motion passes and I look forward to meeting all of you in in the coming days and weeks ahead and working with you. I don't know if you have any questions at all.
Okay, now I'll open up to questions from all the members of the committee. Please, Councillor Hirsch.
I was actually pointing to Councillor Bennett, although I just do want to say
quickly thank you for your willingness to serve. Thank you. Please, Councillor Bennett. Thank you, Councillor Hirsch. Thank you,
Councillor Collins. Thank you, Mr. Grouch, for taking our questions and your willingness to serve. How can we use CRITS to help promote economic development and equitable economic development here in the city?
Well, I think you've already been doing it. You know, like I said, just the way that Lancaster City has changed just in the last few years and certainly over the last 10 or 15 years or 20 years, I mean, it looks completely different than when I grew up. There's always a new coffee shop opening up, a new restaurant opening up. uh lots of different services for people that uh that need it here in lancaster city um and i think you know i think lexington city has become a place where people want to do business because it's a good place to do business and i think that we want to keep that going and quite honestly um i don't want to take any credit for anything because i think that obviously the good work has been done by those who came before me and i just want to continue to help chris uh move forward and certainly help the city uh as they've been doing but uh they've obviously been doing a great job thus far thank you for answering and that includes my questions
i have to say my name yes okay susie gomez 100 block of north reservoir street um are you filling in the position on a legal standpoint or are you filling in the position on a board member standpoint board member position just the board
members thank you thank you now I'll make a motion to move this nomination to our next full council meeting second all in favor aye the second item is the nomination of Jessica Emi for reappointment to the board of health Jessica has been serving on the board for 18 months just for the record she completed the term of another public health educator who retired and stepped down from the board and she has expressed her interest in continuing to serve on the board are there any questions or comments from members of
committee from council council colleagues thank you um i just wanted to thank jessica for wanting to continue to serve on this board it is active and we appreciate her service thank you madam
president for your comment are there any other questions comments now i'll make a motion to move this nomination to our next council meeting second all in favors all right that concludes special committee and I'm president thank you very much councillor cleats
will next move to our Finance Committee councillor Arroyo thank you comes
president we have one item on our agenda this evening its administration bill number 1 2025 with us which is authorizing the issuance of general obligation bonds we had previously heard a presentation from director Campbell on the list of items that this bond issuance would be for like to invite director campbell to the podium to talk about the bill that's in front of us director campbell
thank you good evening everyone um yeah as i mentioned at the february 3rd city council committee meeting we're introducing tonight an ordinance for a 2025 general obligation bond in february as councilor arroyo stated we provided you with a list of general project groupings that this bond would include and attached to the ordinance this evening is a more detailed list of projects that will be included in this bond I also brought paper copies which I passed out earlier that might be slightly easier to read and Daryl Peck who's our financial consultant is handing you some more information that he will provide some details on later when I'm through with my initial comments here so in February I noted that this bond would consist of a proposed total of 55.3 million in projects this number has gone down to approximately 38.4 million in financing for projects so I want to take a few minutes to review the changes I also just want to note I don't think I mentioned this in February we typically we typically look at projects for a bond that will either be completed or nearly completed within three years so this funding would mainly be spent over the next three years the bond consists of funding for three of our funds so the general fund as well as the water enterprise fund and the sewer or wastewater enterprise fund the general fund has not changed since the presentation in February so 19 million of this bond around half of it would be used towards projects that are associated with the general fund the projects themselves also haven't changed we've simply broken them down more in the detailed list that we provided to you this evening and and with the packet so there's still six main categories of projects and I'll just run through those really quickly one would be implementing the parks plan the parks master plan that was approved for a variety of projects in a variety of our parks our vision zero work is another category the continued work on our active transportation plan maintenance to our facilities based on our facilities conditions assessments and this grouping also includes a small match that we needed to satisfy grant requirements for the Welcome Center renovations another category is upgrading our operations center for better efficiencies and then the final category is just kind of general public right-of-way upgrades so these include traffic signal signals streets streetscapes and and that type of thing moving to the enterprise funds then decreases were made in both the sewer and water funds since our presentation in February I'll note that these changes are not a result of ultimately needing less debt financing so rather we determined that we will pursue pen best financing for a couple of projects based on the timing of the projects and also pen best loans have significantly lower interest costs and just to note penvest is a is a state revolving loan fund and this is a fund that can only be used for specific projects mainly in water and sewer and some stormwater projects as well so I'm going to start with changes in the sewer fund we are proposing 10.3 million and financing in this in this bond which is down from about eighteen point seven million that we proposed in February we have three combined sewer separation projects that we need to complete and a portion of all the all three of those projects have been included in this bond mostly for design and engineering work that Penvest will not support but the remaining we've pulled out to pursue with Penvest at a later date that financing will likely not be pursued I'm looking at Molly until 2026 and we'll come back to Council when we're ready to pursue that funding. The general project buckets for sewer do remain unchanged from February. So there's still a portion of the funding, as I just mentioned, for the combined sewer separation, work on our long-term control plan, work to design a new anaerobic digester, improvements, expansion, rehabilitation for some of our aging collection system, emergency escrows to support projects that rise in conjunction with our partners and camera track which we discussed a bit in February as well and then the last enterprise fund included in this bond is the water fund so we're proposing by bond financing in this bond of about nine point one million this has also gone down from a February estimate which was approximately seventeen point six million and this decrease is again due to pursuing penvest funds I'm going to talk a little bit more about this decrease because it's all related to one project which is the 42 diameter water transmission main replacement we've talked about this project often both in financial aspects with capital planning but also in numerous public works reports it's a very large project it must be completed because the current main is well past its usable life and this project will likely total about 41 million dollars to complete we've received a three million dollar grant for the project but the rest of the project will need to be financed so pen best requires that projects be shovel ready before they will loan funds so all the design engineering permits etc must be completed and because of the timing for the grant funds and some of the current uncertainties for timing of procurement of equipment we had initially thought that we would include some of this project in the bond to ensure that we would be able to start to order the equipment and use the grant funds before we would be ready to get a loan through through Penvest however as we reviewed this further and had further conversation with Penvest we decided to pull that funding out completely from the bond and potentially pursue interim financing in the next couple of months to cover these costs Penvest will not refinance permanent or bond financing however interim financing will allow us to move all the costs eventually into a penvest loan as they do allow interim financing to be included once the loan is actually ready to be dispersed this will keep interest costs down very significantly for us and will make interim financing well worth it to save on that interest expense so I'm saying all these details for two reasons tonight one is because because we anticipate that we'll need this funding for the water main over the next year we're including this debt in the projections that you'll see from daryl that he just handed out and he will talk about in a few minutes because the debt will affect basically the same operating budgets as the bond we want to show them at the same time and two we will be returning over the next couple of months possibly even as early as next month with with details of the debt of the interim financing for you to review as well So that's really the the main changes in the that's really the main change in the water fund since February There's three other general categories water quality improvements We need to do some design work for the PFAS work and lead line replacement But those were all on the previous list and those groupings haven't changed So I think I'm gonna stop there and turn it over to Daryl to provide some additional financial information and talk about the debt schedules of it
Thank You Tina Good afternoon. I'm sorry. Good evening members of council. Thank you for being let me be here tonight to work with you the presentation I handed out to you and is Will look similar for those of you who might have been here about three years ago when the last you know multi-purpose financing was done so We're ultimately gonna be doing one what would you what do you call one bond issue? but we we try to tailor each piece you have a general fund component you have a sewer fund component and you have a water fund component so it's really kind of almost three financings and one obviously you're economize on the on the related costs but the key being you know we're really kind of thinking about this and we're also tailoring the terms and the structures of each three component to best manage none of the useful lives of the respective projects but also the budgetary impacts so when we get to the graphs a lot of people some people like numbers some people like graphs I think the graphs pretty much show a pretty good picture of kind of where you're going or where you are and where you're going and I'll talk about timing then on the back end so if you join me on page one this is what I'm talking about about the general fund I'm gonna do the high level of each fund and I'm going to go kind of vertical so the general fund is for the 19 million dollars of projects the sewer fund and that will be over a term of 20 years again kind of tailoring the useful life of the respective projects the sewer fund is as products of about 10.3 million dollars we're going to finance those over a term of 30 years the water fund about nine $9.1 million and we're going to finance that over a period of 25 years for a total projects of the 38 almost thirty eight and a half million dollars. So now we're going to talk each fund kind of individually So for the general fund of the 19 million dollars in projects we start with where you are So that line row two there is the existing net debt service for the respective funds. So Your current general fund debt service is about seven point five million dollars with financing the 19 million dollars certainly you've already adopted a budget for 2025 so we have no budgetary impact for the remainder of 2025 in any of the funds also just to allow time for your for your obviously the projects to be done and also to replenish some of your reserves with with any of the increases you've had recently here in 2025 we're not going to have any budgetary impact in the general fund in 2026. So you'll remain at $7.5 million. Then the impact from this borrowing in 2027 will be about $900,000. So you'll settle in at about $8.4 million. And there'll be no further impact or increases in 2028. So the overall budgetary impact of this borrowing will be the $900,000. And then when we get to the graphs, you'll see how it actually steps down in the future but it'll never there's not another increase coming is what I'm trying to say sliding over to the sewer fund the ten point three million dollars of projects your current existing debt services just under four point seven million dollars in 2025 again for the remainder of the year there'll be no budgetary impact in 2026 even with this borrowing your debt service or budgetary impact is going to be what we'll call a modest $120,000 because your existing debt service is already dropping down okay and we'll see that in the graph and really there'll be no future increases beyond 2026 so the overall impact or budgetary impact of the sewer borrowing is $120,000 going forward and again you'll see step downs when we get to the graph. Water fund, for the $9.1 million of projects, your existing 2025 debt service is $14 million. Again, no increase in 2025. In line five there, the additional impact in 2026, this was a little bit different. So that $1,071,000 that you're seeing, that's actually what's going to happen even if you weren't borrowing another dollar today. So So, yes, you're going to have a budgetary impact or an increase in 2026 of about a million dollars. Again, all of that is already of projects you've previously done and what's in your current budget going forward. Then we're going to kind of take a year off in 2027. And then in 2028, as a function of this borrowing, the budgetary impact will be that $938,000. dollars so sum total of the million dollars that or it was there and the nine hundred thousand dollars from this borrowing your overall budgetary impact in 2028 will be about two million dollars I'm gonna pause there again I think the graphs are going to show this much better but and so those are the borrowings and the budgetary impacts from this financing any questions on that before I it's a function of the useful lives of the projects that are there they're in the project list that you was handed out there are useful lives of the respective projects I kind of did it like a mathematical calculation to get kind of an average life and we're being careful that you know it's like your car you don't you know you don't borrow for your car for ten years when you know you're going to need a new car in five. So we're doing the same thing with the projects that you're financing. We're being careful that, and also it's appropriateness. You don't want to, while you don't want to finance something longer, if you don't need to, why financing something shorter and have a higher burden today just to kind of save a lot more money tomorrow? It's not always equitable. So we try to balance the terms of the financing with the respective useful lives of the projects being financed.
Mr. Peck, can you just clarify, so when you say impact, this is effectively the budgetary impact insofar as this is the interest and other costs that are associated with the financing itself?
It's those yellowed numbers that I'm referring to as a budgetary impact. Those are the increases in debt service. going back yeah on top of what you currently have row two so those are the that's the new that's the additional annual expense on top of what you
already have interest expense actually interest in principle okay thank you
yep so the the box at the top again is the is the bond issue or the or the budgetary impact as Tina indicated the water transmission line is kind of right around the corner if you will so we wanted to you know kind of show you what's right around the corner so for the in the water fund only that water transmission main that has a current estimated cost of about 41 million I just want to give you a snapshot and I show it graphically again you know on top of the bond issue being the top top half that we're talking about uh the 41 million dollars as a penvest loan which is what's contemplated and preferred um you're going to have those additional amounts at the bottom in 2026 they'll be interested only of about 476 000 in 2027 about 700 000 in 2028 you'll start paying principal on that penvest loan so it'll be at 1.8 million and in 2029 about 2.4 million just to be clear those are cumulative okay they're not it's not 400 and another 700 okay it may even be possible to have that interest only be what's referred to as capitalized and not have a budgetary impact but kind of wanted to show you more of a more of a worst-case presentation again some of you like numbers some of you might like graphs so on page two is the before and after of general fund the red bars being the existing debt service going forward and the green bars being you know existing in addition to the new borrowing so you know like I showed you in the numbers you're gonna have no increase in existing general fund debt service until in 2027, that rise is that $900,000 I showed you. Actually, in a good way, we're going to still step down or reduce your debt service beginning in 2030 by about $1.1 million. Why? To provide future capacity. You know, if there are additional projects that are going to happen three, four, five years from now, this is providing that budgetary capacity to have additional borrowings in the future. Then again, just like you see, the red bars already do that. So we're really kind of keeping that theme going forward and that budgetary flexibility. Then in 2035, debt service is going to drop another $1.4 million. And then it's going to stay there at that level until 2045. So overall, when you look at these graphs again, you can tell, say, we're extending your debt service two years from a year perspective okay next page is the sewer fund same concept again for 2025 no increase remember I told you that sewer debt services was going to increase about a hundred and twenty thousand dollars well the reason for that is because as you can see the red bars there's already a reduction you know back to what I was saying about about the general fund you know three four or five years from now you'll be potentially adding debt service on a lower base so you know you won't have as much of a budgetary impact then in 2035 your sewer fund debt service that reduction will be about nine hundred thousand dollars again in 2043 about five hundred thousand dollars is that reduction and in 2049 that reduction is about 2.2 million dollars again kind of getting back that equitability and why you financing things earlier here you know we did frankly stretch out the borrowing for 30 years because again it's more appropriate given the useful life of the projects being financed and again this is providing flexibility and you know certainly if you get there and you didn't borrow any money by then you know certainly you could prepaid at that point but so it's really leaving the flexibility for future capacity lastly the water fund this one's a little bit busier because of the concept of the penvest so the red bars here are the existing the green bars are the resulting after this bond issue and in the gold bars are layering over on top yet again that 41 million that contemplated to 41 million dollar penvest loan for the water transmission line you know this this one doesn't this one as you can see is already fairly level in debt service so for the most part it's going to continue to be level there are there there are not step downs in the future you know with with the useful life of of these projects we're using a term of 25 years so again in 2026 that first increase that million dollars you can see the red and green the same because again that's our that increase is already there without this borrowing then the additional increase from this borrowing in the in 2028 set eight hundred thousand dollars you saw from page one and pretty much stays there after 2048 and then would step down again to fill out the 25 years and then the gold bars again are just for even further forward-looking of layering on the contemplated 41 million dollar
but that is later for no not part of this bond issue questions you want you mean sum total is that what you mean before or after okay you're sorry
me a moment I do not have it with existing trying to get back to you I'm
sorry it's I don't know I'm sorry I do you do have it great under that three years 370 million which may be directed to the handle and I mean the since we're doing these projects being that we don't first we really don't know what's how it's gonna happen with all the federal regulations in regards to construction materials would that also possibly cause not being able to have done we have to
come back again and do another loan yeah we have been looking at some of the federal regulations at this point and the the projects that we have included in this we don't feel are going to be necessarily affected by the federal regulations I will say some of the design work that we're doing might be some changes but we haven't put in for construction for those projects at this
point does that am I saying that accurately enough okay if you can talk a little bit about the budgetary impact in the individual funds and how from a budget from a financial planning and you know for the next five years how are these budgetary impacts also being looked at from a planning side yeah I'll maybe take them as
separate enterprise funds here a little bit so for the general fund we have been doing some work with the multi-year projections that we showed you with the budget just to ensure that we're making sure that these are included in those so I mean obviously it affects the budget you can see that in the in the paperwork but it's not what we're not concerned at this point about being able to work with it within the yeah the tax structure that we have currently so we're not anticipating that it would it would make us increase taxes over the next five years for the sewer fund we have been anticipating that this is coming and so we have raised rates so we feel like we're in in pretty good shape for the sewer fund and as you can see again with the sewer fund that current the current debt financing is actually going down a little bit and so we'll be able to manage that one pretty much at the same level that we have been in the sewer fund for the water fund we this is the one we've been looking at the most so we are in the process of submitting a PUC rate case which would hopefully allow us to increase outside city rates to help to offset some of this work we will likely need to go back out for another PUC rate case in about three years and that's the plan at this point in order to work with that increase
again so that that's the plan for those projections correct yes so um Dale
didn't talk about this but some of the work that he did in the kind of amortization is really to stack some of those so for example there's a couple are five years or ten years those are actually that financing is actually um shown more at the beginning of the the term so that doesn't stretch out as long okay and that concludes my questions
thank you councilman any questions from council council thank you uh counselor all right my
question um could perhaps go to either director campbell although um it's just a very general question and it is some of the projects that are listed in this i know are are not maintenance but they're extending the useful life of the assets so they're almost like rehabilitation and not repair so to speak and then there are also some projects i'll just use the design of the anaerobic digester as an example where um and the the camera truck is another one of these where will actually result in cost savings to what extent does the city put together analysis to understand how some of these investments in the long term will save on money not even necessarily return on investment analysis but is there an understanding of how some of these projects could save the city money in the long run and what those savings would be do you want to speak to that
Thank you very, very much for the question. There's a lot of discussion internally about what are the best ways to not only build, but materials to use, means and methods, which are technically not the responsibility of the designer. But we talk about that a lot because materials and methods go to what it's going to cost to maintain or operate the facility. sometimes that means looking at equipment that is obsolete the factor machine for instance is is one where which has a useful life of 20 years if that's an extraordinary amount of time for this kind of equipment but it's necessary to be able to cost-effectively maintain the infrastructure that we're talking about in other cases we look at the location of the infrastructure to be built, what properties need easements, what properties need to be acquired, or what kinds of construction methods are required to build that particular work. So there's a lot of often cost-benefit analysis in the nature of the early discussions. Our consultants are asked constantly, is this the best way to do this? What are not only the capital cost implications, But the operations cost implications. Are we going to have to hire more people to take care of this particular infrastructure in this particular way? Or can we maintain it basically with the current staff but with different equipment? Sometimes we're making a decision about technology. Is it technology that will not only maintain or improve the water quality, but is it technology that will reduce the cost maintaining that there's a as a municipal run utility there's a lot of that kind of balancing act that we're that we often are doing because we don't have the ability to go for the hottest most expensive shiniest often most efficient way of doing it we don't have the ability to raise the rates at the levels that the private private utilities do and yet we are required and and are very proud of the fact that we meet the same standards that all the other utilities do. So these are constant discussions. Almost every one of our discussions, especially with our consultants and when we're talking about the sewer fund, we're also sharing these costs with several outside municipalities. And so they, too, query us about, is this the best way to do it, the most effective way to do it, the most efficient way to do it, the best equipment to do it? To what extent do they have to be part of that solution to what extent do can we reduce or delay or phase the work in a different way that's always an integral part of the discussion thank
you director Campbell that's good to know that the other municipalities are are looking to collaborate in that way thank you actually before before
director Stephen Campbell I want to kind of call back to something we've been talking about the last couple of years on council and it relates to what you were just mentioning as far as planning goes but I just could you just talk a little bit about the ways that we have been planning for like these particular projects not just on this list before us tonight or last month but over the last several years because I think that's an important piece of this puzzle is how I we got to these particular set of projects and why i'm very happy to talk a little bit about
about that type of discussion up until relatively recently i would say up until the last few years maybe three three to five years ago we often did our capital planning based on what was on the immediate horizon what we saw if we walked around what we perceived as the work that needed to be done or the challenges that were directly in front of us with when transit breaks for instance it's cataclysmic it it doesn't just break that line it often breaks in very a variety of places in the same neighborhood by developing a long-term capital plan where we can look up to 30 years ahead in fact up to 32 years ahead it gives us a lot of flexibility in terms of what we need to do when we need to do it and how what are there are options to do it differently the one of the key I would argue in and Tina may say differently but one of the key ways that we were able to say that we can reduce some of these costs in this particular bond at this particular moment is because we had a long-term enough horizon to say this work has to get done no later than 2040 or no later than 2030 or something like that, not that it has to be done immediately or that it has to be at a particular level of performance. The capital planning effort, not only in terms of the horizontal infrastructure, which is the water and wastewater, but the vertical infrastructure, which are our buildings represented in our facility condition assessments, which is the work that we completed about two years ago, allows us to say, with some level of predictability, it's not always perfect, and it's not always down to the day or down to the month. But one can say that this particular asset, the windows in this building, generally speaking, have a remaining useful life of 11 years. And so at year eight, you need to be planning to replace those windows, rather than looking the way we had before and say, I see a bunch of windows that are broken. Do we need to replace all of the windows? Yeah, let's replace all the windows. That was expedient, but not planning-wise. Now we have that ability, not only in the vertical infrastructure, but the horizontal infrastructure to do that. And we're going to continue doing that. One of the reasons to have much of the camera equipment is to be able to see internally to not only the wastewater lines, but the water lines as well, what their conditions are and what can be sealed, what can be done differently and cost effectively. Some of the linings that we do, for instance, give us an additional 30 to 40 years of useful life of some of the infrastructure, whereas previously we might have had to think of just replacing that infrastructure outright. So lining the infrastructure is significantly less expensive to do and gives us cost effectively the level of performance
we're looking for can I just add to that too big thanks to Steve and his team for
the capital plan work that's been done but also this has gone through as Steve suggested a number of different iterations. So it started with, here's what we're seeing as what we want, and me saying, here's what we feel like the budget can handle, and then kind of working to come to an agreement on that. And the capital plan has helped us to do that.
Both are necessary. Thank you.
Can I just make one quick correction to Councilor Diaz's question earlier? We had said it was $372 million. It's actually $391 million, so it was closer to the number. Yes.
That's the way I calculated it. I didn't even know. Exactly.
Hey, Director Campbell. Director Campbell. Oh, Councilor Cleese.
Thank you, Councilor Hoyo. I just have one question. When you plan all these projects, do you take into consideration unexpected risks or challenges during the execution of those projects?
Yeah, I, again, will answer first Steve, and then he can correct me if I'm wrong. But there's always a contingency included in the projects well as some um rising costs so if the if the project can't be completed in you know the year that we anticipate then there's also a level of uh you know increased costs that we're um figuring in
as well thank you thank you council please thank you director campbell director campbell and mr peck for the thorough presentations um any questions from the public sorry can i just mention
one more thing um we just want to talk through the the timing a little bit on this so this is an ordinance um we are planning to have the first reading obviously um next week if if that is if it's moved to that point um and then um hopefully the second reading on march 25th um that at least is the anticipated plan for the for the auction do you want to talk about that at all or okay
Yeah so the timing from here would be you know should you move move this forward favorably to council the first reading of the ordinance would be at the March 11th meeting and then we'd have the bond auction and the second reading or enactment of the ordinance at the meeting on the 25th again that's the goal if for some reason we were to get slowed down for some reason you know certainly then we could just push that back to the April 8th meeting so that's the plan moving forward if we make the schedule we're talking about we would have closing towards the end of april so you'd have the funds for the projects then okay thank you for the explanation
with that there's no further questions from council or the public uh i will move uh to send bill number one 2025 to full council on march 11th for its first reading i'll second
that counselor royal um i'll be acting as a member of your committee and counselor
correct thank you council president i have a motion in a second all those in favor aye that concludes the finance committee council president thank you i will now move to public
safety committee council ds thank you president uh the city of lancaster introduced a resolution number 18 2025 which authorized the disposal of certain obsolete police records This action aligns with the retention and the disposition schedule for records of Pennsylvania municipalities. As outlined in the municipal records manual, the city has obviously committed to following up the schedule through the resolution of No. 7 in 1975. The resolution allows the Police Bureau Records Supervisor to dispose of specific, outdated records, ensuring compliance with the state guidelines for the municipal record management. Is there any questions from the committee? Okay, any questions from full council? Any questions from the public?
Question, do we know how far back?
At this time, timeframe-wise, the list says some of them go back as far as 2018 or as recent as 2021, depending on the category that they're in, and that's in line with the per municipal record.
so do we know if records will be destroyed that has counselors at
protests against the police officers around 2020 so you said from 2018 there's a category of citations animal complaints abandoned vehicles and permits and related applications on this list so public as well isn't there public citations meaning traffic and non-traffic it says i don't beyond that i don't i can't speak to specifics we
weren't provided with the specifics just a list and they're asking those documents be destroyed
within a five-year period not 20. this is the disposition schedule for the municipal records
manual that Councilor Diaz outlined. Thank you. If there is no other questions, I'd like to move this to full council on March 11th. Second. All in favor? Aye. And that concludes the safety committee. Thank you, Councilor Diaz. We'll move now to Public Works. Councilor Hirsch. Thank you, Council President. Public Works Committee does not have any legislative items tonight. However, we are receiving a presentation from the Public Works Department.
department on trees for people so while they're getting the technology set up i want to um thank you very much for our opportunity to describe to you the trees for people program it's an initiative from um just before i got here uh which culminated in a report in 2020 i believe and at that point we hired a or shortly thereafter we hired our first urban forester who did some great work with us for a while and then unfortunately left we have since hired another great urban forester who will be giving this presentation to you I introduce you to Molly dagger this if you haven't met her before she's the deputy director for sustainability in the environment which is where and how the city of lancaster fits in the natural environment and she will introduce mike in turn
good evening health members i'm pleased to be here today to share in updating you all as director campbell mentioned on lancaster's urban forestry program this is an effort that continues to grow in both impact and engagement at the heart of this work is our new urban forester mike meyer who in just six months has not only advanced the city's urban forestry initiatives but has truly embraced lancaster's community and culture guided by the 2020 trees for people action plan the city's efforts are expanding from securing funding for hundreds of new street trees this year to navigating challenges such as the suspension of federal funding despite these hurdles our commitment to a greener more resilient lancaster remains strong driven by community partnerships and a belief that trees are essential infrastructure improving air quality cooling neighborhoods and enhancing overall well-being this aligns with the broader sustainability and environment vision which recognizes that lancaster thrives when its people and environment thrive together and with that i'd like to turn it over to dr meyer who will walk you through the latest program updates and community engagement efforts shape excuse me shaping lancaster's tree canopy thank you
you for the introduction so as a quick reintroduction to the trees for people plan this is the city's plan for improving our urban forests and also making sure that everyone in the city no matter their location or status has access to the benefits of trees and that natural environment it's a really well done plan and it says a lot about the city's passion for its residents and the environment that they put together such a wonderful plan most cities and municipalities while maybe they have ordinances or rules or regulations that help try to foster more canopy this plan truly is very encompassing and And definitely the envy of many other municipalities. We have been working very hard to get external funds to help support the mission of the Trees for People Plan. I have a couple of examples I want to go over real quick. We'll start with our USDA U.S. Forest Service. This was a very large grant, $1 million, which would have at least planted 500 trees by 2028. that does even sort of like while I do love planting trees as an urban forester I really like planting trees we we're gonna plant a bunch of trees but this also would have given us support for you know pruning maintenance these all sorts of other additional things that aren't just planting trees because obviously trees have to go somewhere improvements of those tree wells and such finding new tree wells and whatnot sadly this funding has currently been suspended though we are ever so hopeful that it will come back online so that we can get access to it however despite that we are moving forward and onward as well now for this summer we are very excited because we have at the urban forest reset project these are ARPA funds through our clean water partners and going to be planting 376 street trees throughout the city. This is a very holistic grant in that not only are we removing stumps or filling in empty well sites with new trees but we're also improving sidewalk and curb that have been damaged previously by the trees in the immediate vicinity of the tree and as part of that we also have a public-facing front of this and I might actually have to end my presentation for a second and so with a forward-facing app we have easy access for residents to be able to go and take a look at all of the various sites that are we are improving we can you know zoom in we can you know you can search for an address but also for every point it tells you about the work that is going to go on there and so we're hoping to expand on this where possible with more info as the project goes on additionally for some general program updates we are very excited about the new asset management program the city view City Works dual set they're being able to multi-dimensionally track and account for many of the tree related assets of the city really opens up a lot of interesting analyses so that we can better manage our system and more easily and effectively make changes to our tree canopy and other things as well we're hoping to do some ordinance updates and just today we relaunched the trees website so it's been nice and redone which is just a big update from the previous one and so some of just the highlights here because you can all take a look at it if you search for trees on the city website we now have a click it sorry I fix it link right at the top there because that is one of the most pressing issues whenever there is often someone's looking for information on their tree it may wear it very well be because there's a branch down or whatnot they'd like to come in and report it they do a search this is usually where it takes them so now we can get even quicker access to that in addition to that it we go over more of our benefits of trees and we are really promoting our street tree planting program which helps residents get new trees so that if a tree does you know fall or have to be removed we can very quickly and more readily replace those trees additionally but off of that we have been doing plenty of tree plantings we had a large one in cullington park last november which was very successful was a very uh large community event uh through our partners at so we um there was music there was dancing there was food and we got to plant a bunch of trees i mean that sounds like a good time um in addition to that through this month we're also starting uh some plantings uh through various trainings or community partners actually had a street tree planting just this weekend um as part of the new lancaster county tree tenders group so that's really great that was um over by brightside church um through april we're also going to be beginning the planting for the urban reset urban forest reset program and so that will then of course be a lot of improvement through the city there spring and fall are our big times for that and so we're excited about the spring planting additionally we have been growing our community partners most of the photos that we have through this I've tried to really highlight a lot of the community partners we have whether it be uh so we or the alliance or others uh throughout there's there's so many and they've all been very helpful including numerous uh neighborhood groups that have started to pop up um and so as we go through that we're able to more and more better and effect more effectively um communicate with the public get them involved because everyone needs to be involved and have a buy-in to uh you know this very critical part of city infrastructure um if you know you're going to have a tree planted in front of someone's house you want them to be very happy about that tree because then they'll be careful about it they'll care for it especially until it gets big enough that it can kind of care for itself or at least big enough that then it turns from i have to care for it to now i'm worried about what's going on with those branches which is where that transition happens uh as uh my closing slide i'd say if anyone is interested in getting involved um please reach out again um one of the things that uh the trees for people plan i think very uh uh effectively uh says is that you know we have these trees they are for people they are for us we are a city filled with people doing um their everyday lives and um we need to make sure that uh the resources the natural resources around them are working for them and effectively and unless we have a lot of community engagement we're not going to meet any of those goals and so that is one of the things we strive for and i hope we've been doing fairly well so thank you thank you all so much honestly
i spoke right when i see this presentation it's it's a it's it's wonderful in so many ways you note I feel like I see street treats as something that if the city invests in in the short term has huge long-term benefits in so many different ways and the fact that you all are engaging the community in it I think that's it gives all of us a sense of ownership over our city and I just think that's really really wonderful so really excellent work guys I will open it up to questions comments from the public works committee council council president thank you councillor hirsch
thank you for the presentation this evening it's nice to meet you uh officially uh thank you could you speak a bit about i know that there are probably some residents who have uh have had bad experiences with street trees in the past and uh could you speak to ways that this new plan addresses concerns about what trees are planted in empty wells or replanted uh where there are stumps and where trees may have caused damage to sidewalks before yeah so um i want to address that
in kind of two different ways uh the first one is process uh especially since i started i've been working with um various people within the city to make sure that we have a a good effective process for addressing these concerns like when a tree branch comes down or when someone needs to have assistance and I think we've been working very well about that we've made some significant improvements in the last month or so in parts of that and so as especially as the City Works City View programs come online that is also going to make things much easier as it will sort of very well streamline things will be all electronic we won't necessarily have to have people call in or or maybe just through like the fix it link so when it comes to making it more readily available more intuitive to get those resources I think we're going in the right direction the second part is more you know how are we addressing you know our art where our trees are placed And so one of the big things I always like to say is more tree equal more better with the caveat of the right tree in the right spot and One of the things I'm sure we all are aware of is that if we're wandering through town The sidewalk is not necessarily the most level at times. Sadly that does have to do with some of our trees That also is probably related to the fact that we have nearly a quarter of the city trees being maples historically they've been very easy to get and the plant but because of how they work in their ecosystem as some of the first ones in there they put down shallow roots they really grow them and push them out and then of course the sidewalks kind of suffer that those sorts of decisions were at the time very much like we need a tree we're gonna put something in there we are being far more systematic about that I actually just redid our citing guidelines to make sure that when there we are either planning a well or planning work around the well we're keeping in mind now the subsurface infrastructure more of those clearances um and we are doing um more to make sure that that tree that we put there is the one that will work for the long you know the long haul um so you know the really the best time to plant any tree is like 20 or 30 years ago but the second best time is now so we want to make sure that when we do put those in in the next 20 or 30 years people aren't wondering like what is going on with this tree in a bad way we wanted to be like what's going on with this tree in a
good way any other question or comment from in regards to replacing some of trees do you have like specific trees that you might have found that they're disease that need removal is there any issues I mean I know one particular one that has not been removed and it's causing especially when the wind is really blustery it's it actually damaged someone's car and the neighborhood is concerns I'm curious about other you know what what exactly plans you have to remove to remove these disease trees yeah so with the processes I talked
about we have definitely made some improvements again over the last couple months so that if we have someone with a tree that is problematic we can more quickly address it in the past we have not been as quick at times for that the city arborist and I have been working together to make sure that when we identify a problematic tree we are now more quickly and aggressively starting those next steps to either you know address that if it's like an emergency there's an imminent hazard or if it is just hazardous which is in the professional realm a different level of hazard or something that will fail in the long term like where we're working to make sure that we get ahead of that more with community members especially since for our size municipality every property owner is responsible for the maintenance and upkeep of the street trees and the sidewalk in front of their property this is a piece of information that a lot of people are not familiar with that is part of our ongoing
outreach efforts especially as the planting season moves on for that
particular one that I think you're referencing we're right now just kind of moving through the process it should be figured out within the next month or so
I will let the residents know in that area. Thank you. Thank you.
And if I can just add one point to your initial comment, Councillor, one of the things that I've observed that I really appreciate with respect to the risk of disease and things like that is the intentionality with respect to biodiversity and really it's beautiful to observe a line of trees that are all the the same species, but if that particular tree species then becomes susceptible to disease, you're now talking about eliminating a whole block or having a whole block of trees become at risk. And so with these process improvements, there's a real intentionality to make sure that we're diversifying the types of trees that are all right for that particular instance to be able to be more resilient.
Is there any type of metrics or studies or any type of research that shows a particular tree or trees in general that have more susceptibility of becoming disease? I'm sure that there are particular ones, but I'm familiar only with a few trees. I'm not, I have allergies around this season, so trust me, I stay inside. But I was just curious about that. That's a good question.
I made some promises that I wouldn't get too involved in talking about the tree inventory database, because I'm super excited about it. But I will say that we are very aware of certain species having certain problems. It's a nature kind of thing. We, of course, have the ash trees, which we've had some problems with due to the emerald ash borer. course Dutch elm disease affecting the elms which is why we now have a new variant that we've been planting but as to the earlier question about like planting smarter I have been growing and making our tree database something that we can do these assessments on like trees that we know have these particular issues we can do some spatial analyses another reason I'm excited about having the new asset management there is that we can then start to look at time um more so than just kind of us like oh look this is what we have at the moment um you know i'd like to know like do honey locusts do they start shedding branches when they're like 15 years old um do cherry trees really only last 30 years here like are there issues with diseases on trees that are just due to local issues within the city that are just unique to the city of lancaster um so i would like to utilize our data um just better and more dynamically um so that we can't address some of these things we can be proactive on it we can say oh we have a whole lot of these particular trees in this area we now know that like if they get to be this age or this size maybe they have this problem we can start to like oh let's go and keep an eye out here do we need to do maybe some maintenance or or talk to residents about these sorts of concerns just
remember which tree i really like the albavita tree no but the geometry is very once it starts getting larger it's really hard to maintain but thank you so much for that information no problem
any other uh comment or question from full council i'll also open it up if there are any questions
or comments from the public how we're doing my name is jose 100 block of coral street co-founder of the west crystal volunteers the issues on the trees very good so park between first street so street there's a park right there crystal park now whose responsibility is going to be now to trim those trees and there are no those uh neighborhood parks another thing why we're planting how many trees because we also do have other non-profit organizations doing the same thing planting trees how many trees we need we just eliminated i don't know how many trees there were at least 200 years old just to put a new park and to give it an eye view but what they did was take all the trees off what kind of eye view is that you just took the most important thing out of that park and that's behind the water street mission ridiculous um the park where i'm at uh we take care of that park the gentleman right here in front of me knows that uh you guys that come to pick up park cleaning uh the only thing the guys have to do when they go to check the park clean it it's just to take the bag out of the garbage can because everything else is it's clean my kids already took care of that for the past six years we're still slow on maintenance in that area it's taking forever sometimes because it takes too long to get the part you need for it and all to this red tape i don't want to hear the race red tape that park we have and every other park is very important safe zone for the kids and that's what we're doing we're where but we're still missing a lot of items you guys want to plant more trees we still planting the water sewage running water that will go into the ground we're still doing uh for the disabled to have a wheelchairs we're still doing the corners they're still doing ugi i mean are you guys serious trees that's a waste of money so like i say thank you are there any other comments or
questions from the public thank you so much it was wonderful thank you thank you very much
Councillor Hirsch. We'll now move to our community planning committee. We're going to have Councillor Roy to chair that this evening and Councillor Peck's absence. Thank you, Council President. We have three items on the agenda for this evening's community planning committee. Administration resolution number 2025, 2022, excuse me, 2022-2025 and bill number 2-2025. We'll start with administration resolution number 2025 amending the sewage facilities plans to include the five 50 on fellow drive subdivision um with that happy to invite uh miss logan i believe she could speak
to this resolution good evening thank you um this resolution is related to the sewage facilities plan i'm sure you guys are all familiar with having to pass these um this project is um making sure I have the right is for a single building that is going to be turned into four apartments. So right now it's currently a vacant lot. So they need to have a switch planning module to add those four units for EDUs. Thank you. And yeah, these are regular
current tech council thank you for the explanation on that one um any questions from council or the committee on this resolution any for the public great uh i will motion to move resolution number 2025 excuse me 20 2025 uh to full council on march 11th second all those in favor thank you uh and we'll move to the second item on the agenda administration resolution number 22 2025 amending the sewage facilities plans plan to include the 617 fremont street
project thank you um this is for the construction of three new single family attached dwellings
located at 617 fremont street similar resolution as the first item in expanded sewer capacity any questions from the committee or full council from the public i will motion to move resolution number 22 2025 to full council on march 11. second all those in favor aye aye thank you thank you third item on our agenda is administration bill number two 2025 amending the zoning ordinance and director delphs is already at the podium for this one good evening good evening everyone it's good
Good to see you. Yes, the action before you tonight is related to an amendment of the zoning ordinance. It's a specific amendment related to Price Elementary School. You may remember it was last year that the council took action on a property transfer-related issue. The intent here is that there is a partnership happening between the City of Lancaster, the School District of Lancaster, and the Lancaster Rec Commission. You may remember from the property transfer action that the main thing happening there is a portion of SDOL land is being transferred to the Lancaster Rec Commission. So the former Price Elementary School is going to become a new Lancaster Rec Center, where they will offer additional recreation and child care services. In addition to that, there will be the construction of a new elementary school, Price Elementary School, just to the north. And that will be on the land of the existing recreation center. So essentially what's happening is there's a property transfer and a land swap of sorts. One thing that is important to note is that even though the school district of Lancaster is going to be building a new building, is going to be expanding its footprint. There are conditions and requirements that all of the current Brandon Park facilities and amenities will remain in place and that they're available to the community for those park purposes. So that's the backdrop. I just wanted to give you a little bit of the history that we've already gone over that ground. The zoning amendment that is before you tonight is to make sure we're making the underlying land use changes to support these property changes. In particular, there is going to be an expansion of the parks and open space zoning district. And in addition to that, I'm sorry, as part of that action, there is a map amendment and a text amendment. Our plan is to provide a more in-depth presentation to you all on March 25, and then again on April 8. As you may remember, in the past when we've done zoning ordinance amendments, it's a multi-step process. It's fairly involved. We have the two readings. We have an official hearing. We also, in the background, have public notice requirements, advertisement requirements, all of that good stuff. So the point tonight was really just to introduce the legislative action to provide the context for that action, and ultimately to let you know that we're not really doing anything at the next regular meeting on March 11. But we are planning to provide a presentation on March 25, as I said, and then again the hearing on April 8. So if there are any procedural questions, I'm happy to answer those about what's coming up in the next month or so. Also, if there's anything that you'd like to discuss related to the backdrop or the context,
happy happy to do that as well with the timeline of the project thank you
that's a great question um we actually have a very detailed project schedule that is related to a number of these components in addition to the zoning amendment for example there's also a land development process that is those approvals are required before construction can start as soon as we are able to complete the zoning amendment step then the project will continue through the land development and the planning commission your larger question about the construction of the project we are coordinating that closely with sdol um and and they're aware of uh the milestones in the project thank you thank you counselor any counselor yeah uh director just
a quick question uh you said that there is a hearing on april 8th that's taking place at the
zoning hearing board uh no we're actually gonna have that here uh at council okay so um we'll have to coordinate that with you but the way that we have done this before is we usually open the hearing at the outset of the regular um council meeting and then after the hearing the hearing is officially closed and then if the counselors would like to have additional questions or additional dialogue that uh um that is common and then you would have the choice if you'd like to vote on the matter that night on april 8th or um wait until a later date thank you so much
thank you counselor any additional questions please thank you thank you for your remarks and um how will the proposed amendments benefit the community as a whole thank you we've been working
on this for quite a while now, the three parties like CEREC, SDOL, and the city. The main purpose here is ensuring that we are creating a holistic campus at this particular site around Brandon Park so that we're able to provide the park amenities, recreation services, and a new school to serve the growing elementary school population um if we design if we design this well and we're able to make all of these parts fit together properly then uh we'll be able to achieve all those goals in the same campus and we're very excited about that thank you thank you council please any additional
questions or comments from council from the public thank you director for the context and background
on the ordinance yes much more to come thank you for your patience i know you're going to hear about this a couple more times in the in the coming month or so so appreciate the kickoff
thanks with that i will motion to move administration bill number two 2025 to full council on march 25th for its first reading say again all those in favor aye aye that concludes
the committee of community planning council president thank you very much we'll now move to Committee of the Whole I have two items on that agenda this evening the first item is administration resolution number 19 of 2025 authorizing the appointment of special counsel for collective bargaining director Tina
Campbell good evening again yeah so this resolution is to appoint a special counsel for collective bargaining in consultation with Barry Handwerker our city solicitor we've decided to engage a special counsel starting this year to provide legal counsel in matters related to the collective bargaining agreements for the city's labor negotiations with with the unions particularly this year with the AFSCME union because that's the the contract that will be expiring at the end of the year we decided this year to do this there's been many transitions in city administration some you know key leadership positions myself included as well as the Home Rule Charter and so we just felt it necessary to have outside support for the negotiations this year. So this is to appoint special counsel for that. Thank you very
much. Do we have a context of the cost for retaining special counsel for a variety of we know that we do this for a variety of reasons. Do you have an idea of a cost of this?
So I don't have it depends, it's an hourly rate. So the hourly rate for this is about 365 an hour we wouldn't be using them for all of the negotiation pieces but just to provide counsel so just having them on
retainer does not cost us anything until we decide to use them correct yes thank you other comments from members of council on the resolution
Thank you, Council President. Just one more question on where it's budgeted to. Is this administrative services line item?
It will be partially administrative services. It might also be some of the other departments that are affected by the union negotiations as well.
Thank you very much, Councilor. Any further questions or comments from Council?
Councilor Diaz, can you repeat that again, the cost? Sure, it's $365 an hour.
365 it's a very part it's a very part time so it's just when we when we need a council for negotiations correct yeah yeah any comments from the public on the
resolution hearing none I'll move resolution 19 to our next meeting on March 11th second mr. Harris if you would take a roll call vote on this one
please mr. Mudd aye mr. royal aye mr. Cleese aye
miss Diaz mr. Hirsch hi hi thank you and then councilmembers we also have resolution 21 2025 on our committee of the whole agenda this evening it's recognizing Women's History Month we typically bring this forward I'm proud to introduce it again recognizing the impact of women in the history of both our nation and here at home in lancaster and women from all different backgrounds as well i'll be looking forward to having some folks here hopefully at our next meeting for moving this forward to celebrate them i'll have more information at that time any council comments on the resolution from the public hearing none i'll motion to move uh resolution uh 21 to our meeting on March 11th second thank you mr. Harris if you would mr. man hi mr.
Roya hi mr. Glees hi miss Diaz mr. Hershey hi
president Baker hi thank you members of council our last item on the agenda this evening is the clerk's report which mr. Harris have you provided that in writing to all council members I did thank you very much all right having reached the end of our agenda I'll hear a motion to adjourn motion to adjourn second good all those in favor aye you're adjourned I just want to mention that today is
Puerto Rico citizen